In this video we present the
deterministic model of finite automaton
finite automata are devices that allow
us to describe formal languages
where the description of the language is
given by a mechanism that allows to decide
whether a word belongs
to the language or not
in the processing of each word,
its symbols are considered
in an ordered way and
from left to right
the analysis of each symbol implies a
change in the automaton configuration
the description of formal
languages by finite automata
assumes that there is a finite number
of the different configurations
that the finite automaton
can consider.
As an example let's consider
the language of words over
alphabet a, b, that contain
an odd number of symbols a,
to decide whether or not a
word belongs this language
it is enough to consider the number of
symbols a that have been analyzed so far,
so it is enough to take
into account whether an
even number or an odd number of
symbols a has been processed,
any other consideration
is superfluous.
The different configurations that
a finite automaton can consider
determines the number of
states of the automaton
while the configuration changes
caused by the consideration
of the symbols determine
the transitions
one of the ways to represent finite automata
is the so-called transition diagram.
where each state of the automaton
is symbolized with a circle
that we identify in order to, later, be
able to refer to them individually.
they individually
each of the transitions are
represented by an arrow
labelled with symbols
in the alphabet
it is necessary to indicate the state
where the analysis of any word begins
that state will be marked using an
arrow, in this case the state p
and it also remains to indicate
the final or accepting states,
where, once the analysis finishes, it is
decided if the word belongs to the language
these states will be marked
with a double circle
in this case the
states r and s.
It is important to note that in the
deterministic model, for each
state there are no two outgoing transitions
labeled with the same symbol.
symbol.
To illustrate how a word is processed
in a finite deterministic automaton
consider the automaton
and the word shown.
The analysis considers as a
starting point the initial state
from which the first symbol
of the word is analyzed
taking into account the transition
that is labelled with
the symbol that we are analyzing,
in this case a, as well as
the state that
is reached.
The first symbol has been processed
and state one has been reached,
this is the state to be taken into account in
order to analyze the second symbol of the word.
symbol of the word
The process is the same,
considering the transition
from state one labeled
with symbol b
and the state that is reached,
in this case state two
from this point the following
symbol is processed.
The transition that needs to be considered
at this time of analysis is a loop
that means that there
is no change of state
and we go on to consider the following
symbol, the last of the word.
Again using the outgoing transition
from the active state
and which is labeled with
the symbol to be analyzed
this transition leads to state one
where the analysis of the word ends.
Due to a final state has been reached,
it is concluded that the word belongs
to the language represented by the
determinist finite automaton
Another way of considering the
processing of a word is as the
search for a path labeled with
the symbols of the word
that, from the initial state,
reaches a certain state.
we can represent the path as
shown, enumerating the,
in this case, four transitions
used to process the word.
As a second example of processing we
will consider the same automaton
and the analysis of
the word ababb
the analysis of this word is
summarized in the path shown
that reaches state two,
this state is not final so
the word is rejected,
it's not a word
of language.
The last example of processing
that is shown considers
again the same automaton and,
in this case, the word abab
in this case the processing of
the word cannot be completed
because after analyzing three
symbols there is not an
outgoing transition from the marked state
labelled with the symbol to analyze
despite the fact that the last
reached state is final, because
the processing of the word could not
be finished, this is rejected.
We will now see briefly how to
address the construction of
deterministic finite automata
for a given language.
as the first finite automaton example,
let's consider the previous language
of words over a,b, with
an odd number of as
we have seen that only two
situations are relevant,
thus, we will have two
states in the automaton
in this case the zero state will
represent the situation where
an even number of symbols
a has been processed,
and state one will represent
the situation where
an odd number of symbols
a has been processed.
if, after processing some of a word,
state zero has been reached
it is because an even number
of as are processed,
from this point on the analysis of
a new a implies a change of state
however, the analysis of a b does
not imply a change of state
because it does not change
the number of as processed.
Similarly, if we take into account
that we have processed a
odd number of symbols a, the
analysis of a new a implies
a change of state, while the analysis
of a b does not modify the state
as it does not change the
number of as from odd to even
as we said before, all finite
automata distinguish a state
from which the analysis
of the words begins
in this example before processing
the first symbol of any
word, zero as have been
processed, an even number
so the state zero will
be the initial state.
in this example the set of final
states is limited to state one
because it is the state that determines
that the number of symbols a
analyzed is odd,
therefore, the automaton to be
built is the one shown.
As a second example, let's consider
the language of words over a, b
with at least one b and a
number of as greater than one
to keep track of the number of as
analyzed we will need three states
and we'll need two to control
whether a b has appeared or not
so to control both conditions
simultaneously we will need six states
we will represent with a pair each of the
different configurations that can take place
that is, we have analyzed
zero as and zero bs,
an a and no bs, zero as
and at least one b
more than one a
but none bs,
one a and at
least one b,
and more than one a
and at least one b.
The initial state will be state one and
state six will be the final state
the transitions of the automaton
consider the changes caused by
the processing of each symbol,
thus, from state one
the processing of an a leads to state two
and process one b leads to state three
and similarly you get transitions from
state two, transitions from state three
from state four, from state five,
and, finally, from state six
obtaining the
automaton shown