In this video we will present the
non-deterministic model of finite automaton
we have already seen that finite
automata are devices that
allow us to describe
formal languages
and we have seen that all the states
of a finite deterministic automaton
have, at most, one transition labeled
with each symbol in the alphabet
this makes that in every finite
deterministic automaton only exists
a way to process
each word
the non-deterministic finite automata
model allows the existence
of more than one outgoing transition labeled
with the same symbol for every state
in this way, as well as every
finite determinist automaton
the non-deterministic model also
considers a set of states
a set of transitions, an
initial state, and a set
of states that are distinguished
as final or acceptance states
however, in this model it is
possible that transitions
that start from the same state are
labeled with the same symbol
like those that
are marked.
In the non-deterministic model the processing
of a word concludes with acceptance
if there exists a path that
fully considers the sequence
of symbols of the word and leads from
the initial status to a final state,
initial status to
a final state
therefore, a way of represent the processing
in a finite, non-deterministic automaton
consists of obtaining all
possible analysis paths.
To obtain all these paths
we will build a diagram
which, on the one hand, considers all the states
of the finite non-deterministic automaton
and, on the other hand, the symbols of
the word to analyze in this case abbaba
as in the deterministic model,
the processing of the word
start by considering
the initial state
and every transition from
this state is labeled
with the first
symbol of the word
this example there are two transitions
that reach states one and two
these are the states that are taken into
account to consider the second symbol
in this example
the state one
has two transitions labeled
with the symbol b which is
the one to consider
these transitions reach
the states zero and two
state two also has two transitions
labeled with the symbol b
which also reach the
states zero and two.
Therefore, states zero and two are
the ones to take into account
to analyze the third
symbol of the word
In this case there are no transitions
labeled with the symbol b
from state zero, so only
are considered the
two outgoing transitions
from state two
these transitions reach again the states
zero and two, and we go on to process
the fourth symbol
It happens now that there are only
transitions from the zero state
labeled with
the symbol a
so we reach states
one and two.
which are the ones
we will consider
to analyze the second
symbol from the end.
The situation is identical to
the one we saw in the second
processing step of this word, that
is, the analysis of the symbol b
from states one and two
as we have already seen, the
states reached are zero and two.
and we go on to analyze
the last symbol.
Again a situation that we have already
seen. The analysis of symbol a
from the states
zero and two.
as we saw, the states one
and two are reached.
and the process
is over.
Once this process is finished
the diagram represents all the
different ways of
processing the word
In this case, there exist a
path from the initial state
to a final state
and that this path
is not unique
therefore we can conclude that the
word belongs to the language
represented by
the automaton.
The existence of other paths
that fully process the
word and do not end
in a final state
or even, paths that are not able
to fully process the word
do not prevent the word
from being accepted
by the automaton
since the condition
requires only the existence
of a path leading to
a final state.
Another way to see the analysis of
a word in one of these models
it is to consider that there is a
non-deterministic process that
once considered a symbol of the
word chooses a transition
among the possible,
in this way, and taking into account
the same example, the process would
start from the initial
state of the automaton,
it would consider
the first symbol,
and the outgoing transitions labeled
with this from the marked state
among the marked transitions
the non-deterministic process
that we have mentioned
selects one of them,
which is the one considered to
build the processing path,
and, therefore, the one that determines
the next state to consider
in this point, it is assumed that the
first symbol has been processed
and we take into
account the second.
we proceed in the same way,
selecting the transitions that
are labeled with the symbol to consider and are
outgoing transitions from the indicated state
selecting in a non-deterministic
way one of them
allows to update the processing
path and the state
reached with the
first two symbols
from this state the following
symbol is processed.
The process continues in
the same way by selecting
in a non-deterministic way one
of the possible transitions,
updating the path, and the state
reached with the symbols
that we have already
processed.
This state, again, is the one considered
to analyze the next symbol.
next symbol
The process continues
in the same way
using the state reached by the
non-deterministic process
to process the
following symbol.
And always in the same way,
considering the possible transitions
selecting one of them
updating the way
the reached state, that summarizes
the processing of all
symbols considered
so far.
The non-deterministic process
guarantees that in case that
the word belongs to the language
that represents the automaton
once processed, it is
accepted and one of the
possible paths
of acceptance
With respect to the construction of
finite, non-deterministic automata
there are no general rules that allow
the construction of an automaton
regardless the
language considered,
however, the non-deterministic
model is sometimes
intuitive enough to get a
description in certain languages,
for example, in this case it can be
seen easily that the language that
the automaton shown accepts is that
of words formed by symbols a and b
containing the
segment bb,
because the only way to
access the final state is
to process two
consecutive bs.
The initial loop allows to
process the prefix of any word
of the language to find the bb
segment we're looking for.
The loop on the final state shows
that once this state is reached,
let's say with a word x, it is
accepted as a word of the language,
anyone that contains
as a prefix x,
because it ensures that x
contains the bb secgment.
It is important to mention that, in
general, the non-deterministic model
allows for more concise representations of
languages than the deterministic model
as an example the smallest DFA that
accepts the represented language
for this automaton
has eight states