theme one alphabet
words languages
lesson One
the references shown can help
the study of this lesson
A central concept in the theory
of automata and languages
it's the concept of
formal language
to reach it we will start from
the definition of alphabet
an alphabet is defined as
any non-empty finite set
Its items will be called
symbols or letters
some examples of
alphabets are
the alphabet of two
symbols a and b...
or the set of binary
digits zero, one...
the set of
decimal digits,
or the lowercase letters of the
alphabet are also alphabets
as well as the set of all the different
words contained in Don Quixote
To denote alphabets we will usually
use uppercase Greek letters
as sigma, delta, gamma
Using the symbols of an alphabet,
the words or strings are build
which represent the equivalent of
sentences in natural language.
A word is a finite
sequence of symbols,
to identify words we will use the lowercase
symbols of the Latin alphabet u, v, w, etc.
as examples of words, and
given the alphabet a, b
a and bbab, among others,
are valid words.
Given a word sometimes we
will refer to its length
that is, the number of
symbols that compose it
the length is usually noted by
enclosing the identifier between bars
of the word
as an example if we
consider the word bbab
we see that its
length is four
the existence of the
zero-length word is admitted
this will be denoted
with the lambda symbol
sometimes it will be useful to refer
to the number of occurrences
of a symbol in a word
we denote this number by adding
a sub-index to the bars
which denoted the
length of a word
thus if x is equal
to the word bbab
so the number of occurrences
of symbol a in x is one
and the number of occurrences
of the symbol b in x is three
An interesting set of words
on a sigma alphabet
is the set of words
of a given length n
this set will be denoted using
n as an exponent of sigma
as examples, and given
Sigma equal to a, b
Sigma zero is the set containing
exclusively the word lambda
and Sigma three is the set of all the
words of as and bs of length three
another set of interest is
that of all possible words
we will denote this
set as Sigma star
a little more formally as the
union of all sets Sigma i
where i is an integer
we will also refer to
the whole set of words
over sigma of length
greater than zero
this set will be
denoted as Sigma plus
obviously, the relationship between the
sigma star and sigma mas sets is close
the set Sigma star can be
ordered in different ways
one of them is the
so-called canonical order
this order states that one
word precedes another if
its length is smaller
or if it is before alphabetically
when words have the same length
As an example taking again
sigma equal to a, b
bb is previous to aaa
and aba is
previous to baa
we also show the numbering
of the first words
of sigma star using
the canonical order
an internal operation called
concatenation is defined in sigma star
given two words this operation
returns the word resulting
of arranging the symbols
of the second word after
the symbols of
the first
as examples, it is shown the
result of concatenating
aab and bbab as well as
concatenating lambda and bab
also mention that the dot
operator is usually omitted
We also mention also that the concatenation
is associative and has neutral element
and that it is
not commutative
to shorten the notation when
a symbol or piece of word
repeats n times it is denoted
using exponential notation
in this way given
any word x
x to zero is lambda
and x to one is x
as examples, the result of
aab to the cube is shown
of lambda to the
seventeenth
and of a to two
b to the cube
the reverse of a word
is also defined
as the resulting word of reading
the symbols from right to left
as examples
the reverse of
lambda is lambda
and the reverse of aaba is the same
word since it is a palindrome.
some of the properties of
the reverse are shown
segments of a word are
also defined as any
sequence of
consecutive symbols
every initial segment is a prefix
and every final segment is
a suffix of the word
as an example
given the word
of the screen
some of its
segments are
bac, bb, acc,
and lambda
among its
prefixes are a
aba among others
and some of its
suffixes are
bbacc, the same
word, or lambda
we will denote with x Seg
the set of segments of x
with Pref of x the set of prefixes
of x and with Suf of x the set
of suffixes of x
we show as an example the
sets of segments, prefixes
and suffixes of
the word aba
defined word, alphabet,
and set of all possible
words, we get to the
notion of language
given any alphabet sigma
a language is any set
of words over sigma
that is, any subset
of sigma star
as an example, and given
the alphabet zero, one
the set of all words starting
with zero is a language
what can be more formally
denoted as shown
the set of words with the same
number of zeros and ones
is also a language
which can be easily noted using the
number of occurrences operator
that we have
seen before
Another language, is the set of
words with length less than three
this can be fully enumerated
because it is a finite language
the set of palindromes over
zero, one is a language
what can be noted
using the operator
reverse as shown
Other languages are zero one
star, zero one more, the set
of words of length four
empty language or language
containing exclusively lambda