In this video a set of operations on formal
languages is intuitively presented
of operations on formal languages
is intuitively presented
it is important to note the intuitive
nature of the explanation
and that the study of these operations
implies to consult the bibliography
and the rest of
available material.
The first operation presented
is the quotient of a
language with
respect to a word
given a sigma alphabet
and a language over it
a way of seeing at the quotient
of L respect to a word u
is to consider exclusively
the words of language
that have u as
a prefix,
in such a way that the ratio of L
to the word u can be described
as the set of all suffixes
of u in the words in L
Another equivalent description
of this operation
is to see the quotient of
L respect to a word u
as the set of all words such
that its concatenation to
u on the right. result in a
word that belongs to L.
As a first example to illustrate the
behavior of the operation quotient
let us consider the language of
words over the alphabet a, b
which contains
the segment aa,
the quotient of this language
respect to the word aa
equals the language
a, b star
whereas the quotient of L1
respect to the word bba
can be seen as the union
of two languages:
the one of word over the alphabet
a,b beginning with b, and that
contains segment aa
united to the language of words over
the alphabet a, b beginning with a.
As a second example let us consider
the language of words over
the alphabet a, b containing
an odd number of as
the quotient of this language
respect to the word bab
is equal to the set of words
over the same alphabet that
contain an even
number of as
whereas the quotient of the language
L2 with respect to the word b
is equal to the
same language L2.
We now consider the operations
homomorphism and inverse homomorphism.
As a first step it is necessary to
define the homomorphism operation
which is considered as any total
function h from sigma on delta star.
that is, a function h such that
each symbol of the alphabet sigma
is mapped into a word over
the alphabet delta.
As an example of
homomorphism
let us consider the alphabets sigma equal
to a, b and delta equal to zero, one;
an homomorphism operation can be
defined by considering the image
of a as the word 00
and the image of b according the
homomorphism as the word 1.
The extension of the homomorphism
operation to words
is done by applying the homomorphism
to every symbol of the word
so, for example, the
homomorphism of the word
abba consists on first considering
the homomorphism of a, 00
then the homomorphism
of b, 1
again the homomorphism
and finally the homomorphism
of the symbol a, 00.
Similarly the homomorphism
of the word baba is equal
to the word 100100.
Thus, given an homomorphism
from sigma in delta star
and a language over
the alphabet sigma,
we will consider the set of
words over the alphabet delta
such that, they are an image, according
to the homomorphism, of some
word in the language L.
The set of homomorphisms
of all the words of L
is what is known as the
homomorphism of the language.
An example to illustrate the
behavior of the homomorphism
operation of a language we
consider the language
of words over the
alphabet a, b, c
such that contain as many symbols
a as symbols b and c added
being for example the homomorphism the
one that associates the symbol a
to the word 0, the symbol
b to the empty word,
and the symbol c
to the word one
the homomorphism of the language
is equal to the set of words
over the alphabet zero, one such
that contain more symbols zero
than one such
that contain
at least as many zero
symbols as symbols one.
To define the inverse
homomorphism of a language
given any homomorphism
sigma on delta star
and an L language over the alphabet delta,
we will consider all the words over sigma
whose image according to the
homomorphism belongs to language.
The set of all these words
is what constitutes the
known as inverse
homomorphism of language.
As a first example to
illustrate the behavior of
the inverse homomorphism
of a language
we consider the finite
language shown
and the homomorphism of the alphabet
a, b, c on the set zero, one star
such that it associates the
symbol a with the word 0,
the symbol b to
the word 11,
and the symbol c
to the word 110,
the inverse homomorphism of the language
L is equal to the finite language shown
because the homomorphism of any other
word over the alphabet a, b, c
does not belong to
the language L.
As a second example we consider
the language of words
over the alphabet 0, 1
ending with a symbol 1
and the homomorphism of the alphabet a,
b, c, on words of the alphabet 0, 1
such that it maps the symbol a
the word 0, and the symbol b to
the word 01. The inverse homomorphism
of language L is equal to
set of words over alphabet
ab that end with b.
Finally, we consider the definition
of operations on languages
as the extension of other operations
defined operations on words
when the image of a
word is another word,
in order to define the extension to
languages it is enough to consider the
set of all images of
words in the language.
As an example, considering the
operation reverse of a word
this operation
can be extended
to define the reverse of a
language as the set of reverses
of all words in
the language.
When the result of the operation
on words is a language
the extension is made up
considering the union of all
languages obtained as an image
of a word in the language.
An example is the consideration
of the operation prefixes
of a word,
the extension is made up
considering the union
of the prefixes of all
words in the language.