This video intuitively describes
the boolean operations
on formal languages
we insist on the intuitive
nature of the talk
and refer the student to the bibliography and the rest
of the available material to delve into formal aspects
to delve into
formal aspects
When we refer to
Boolean operations
we do it to three well-known
operations on the set theory
the union, the intersection,
and the complementary
identically to how these
operations are defined in the
mentioned set theory,
given a set of words on
a given alphabet sigma
and two languages
L1 and L2
the union of L1 and L2 languages
consists of considering
all words that belong
either to L1 or to L2,
similarly the intersection
of two languages L1 and L2
is formed by those words that
belong to both languages,
finally, the complementary of a language
L over a given alphabet sigma
consists of the set of words
that do not belong to L
To illustrate the behavior of
these language operations
let's consider initially the
three finite languages shown,
the language L1 formed by
three words: lambda,
ab, and aab; language L2
made up of four words
a, ab, ba, and bbab;
and the language L3 formed
by the words whose length
is less than or
equal to two
the union of L1 and L2
consists of considering
all words that belong
to L1 and L2
the intersection
of L1 and L3
is formed by those
words of L1
having a length less
than or equal to two
and the complementary of L3
is formed by those words
which do not
belong to L3
that is, the words on the
alphabet a, b whose length is
greater than or
equal to three
For a second set of examples
consider the language L1
as the language of words
over the alphabet a, b
containing an odd number of
as and an odd number of bs
the language L2 as the set of
words over the alphabet a, b
with an even
number of as
and the language L3 as the set of
words over the alphabet a, b
which do not contain
the segment ba
the union of the language
L1 and L2 contains
all words over the
alphabet a, b
that have an even number of
as or an odd number of bs
the intersection of
language L1 and L3
contains the words formed by
a sequence of as followed
of a sequence of bs
and where the number
of as and bs is odd
and complementary to L1
is the set of words
with an even number of as
or an even number of bs
we note here that other
operations on languages can
be described as a composition
of Boolean operations
for example, the difference of
languages, that is the set
of words that belong to one of them
and do not belong to the second
can be described as the intersection
of the first language
with the complementary
of the second
As an example, considering
language L1 as the set
of words on alphabet a, b
with an odd number of as
and the language L2 as the set
of words on the alphabet a, b
with an even
number of bs
the difference
of L1 with L2
contains the words
with odd number of as and
a pair number of bs
similarly the symmetrical
difference of two languages L1
L2 contains all the words
that belong exclusively
to one of the two languages,
and can be described
using Boolean operations such
as the intersection of
first of them with the
complementary of the second
united to the intersection of the second of the
languages with the complementary of the first
An example, considering
the set of words on
alphabet a b with an
even number of as
and the set of words over alphabet
a, b with an even number of bs
the symmetric difference contains
those words over the alphabet a, b
such that, if the number of as is
even then the number of bs is odd,
and if the number of as is
odd then the number of bs
in the word is even.