In this video, some operations based on the product
of formal languages are intuitively explained
based on the product of formal
languages are intuitively explained
we point out the intuitive
nature of the explanation
and refer to the student to the
recommended bibliography and
the rest of the material available
to delve into more formal aspects
Of course, this video should begin by dealing
with the product of formal languages
that, given two languages L1
and L2 over a Sigma alphabet,
is defined as the set of
words that can be obtained
by concatenating a word
in the first language
and another word in the second
language, regardless the result
belongs to the
first language,
to L2, or to
none of them.
As a first example, consider the
two finite languages in the image
the product of these languages,
that can be noted using the two
ways shown in
the image,
contains all the words that can
be divided into two factors
the first of them in L1
and the second in L2
As another example, let's consider
the three languages in the image
the first of them is the language
of words over alphabet a, b
that end with a
the second of them is the
set of words on the same
alphabet beginning
with the symbol b
and the third the set of words over
the alphabet a, b with exactly one b
where this symbol is the
suffix of the word.
The product of
L1 and L2
results in the set of words
containing segment ab,
and the product of
languages L1 and L3
results in the set of
words over alphabet a, b
such that ab is a
suffix of the word
Once the product of languages has
been defined, the power of a
language L over an alphabet sigma
is defined as the concatenation
of a serie of words
in the language,
in such a way that the n-th power
of the language is composed by
all the words that are the result
of concatenating n words in L.
As a first example, let us consider
the finite language that
contains only
two words,
lambda and the word a
the third power of this language
contains all the words formed
by a number less than or equal
to three of symbols a.
As a second example, consider the
language formed by the words
which are the result of
concatenating to a sequence
of n symbols b
a symbol a,
the fourth power of this language
contains all the words
with exactly four as being one
of them suffix of the word.
although the n-th power of a
language contains exclusively
the words that can be obtained by
concatenation of n words of L
the concatenation of any number
of words in the language
always returns a word that belongs to
the star closure of the language
this word will also belong to the
positive closure of the language
if at least one of the words of
the language has been considered
another way to define
the star closure of L
or L star, is as the union of
all the powers of language,
similarly, the positive closure
of l or L plus is defined
as the union of all the powers of
the language greater than zero.
As examples to illustrate these
operations we will consider
languages in the
image, L1
that contains only one
word, the word a:
L2 which is also finite and
contains the words lambda
b, ba. and bb; and language
L3 containing the words
formed by a sequence of symbols
b of any length, that end
with a symbol a. In the first
case the star closure of
case the star
closure of l
L1 contains the words formed
by a sequence of symbols
a of any length,
and the positive closure of L1
contains the words formed
by sequences of symbols
of length at least one.
When the star and positive
closure operations are applied
on language L2, results the
same language, that is,
the language of words on alphabet
a, b that do not contain
the segment aa and do not
start with the symbol a.
In the third case, the star
closure of language L3
contains those words
over alphabet a,b such
that a is a suffix of the word,
the word ends with the symbol a,
together with the
word lambda.
Positive closing of the
language L3 contains strictly
the set of words on alphabet
a, b that end with a.